hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference guest stream 69.1 on
February 6th
2024 really looking forward to this
session and conversation with Andrew
mccluhan we will be hearing about
Marshall mccluhan and project 69 so it's
an incredibly
auspicious numerological coincidence and
I look forward to hearing about what
you're GNA share right now Andrew so
thank you very much to
you thank you um yeah well I noticed
that the stream was
69.1 or whatever so uh I thought well I
guess I know what I'm going to talk
about you know actually um numbers
numerology is uh is important in mclan
work maybe not in the fullblown uh
mystical sense of it although that too
some sometimes um but the number 69
comes up a few
times um in a very Villa kind of way um
well Marshall loved the number
three for a few reasons uh the Trivium
was a pet subject of his grammar
rhetoric
dialectic uh there was his PhD work uh
on the
Trivium for example um also the Holy
Trinity you know father son holy
Spirit um and the mouans lived in
Toronto for the longest time at number
three Witchwood Park which seemed
officious to them I'm
sure um you know 693 is is a roote of 69
of
course um Marshall mclone was 69 years
old when he died uh amazingly enough he
wasn't uh that old according you know
people tend to live longer than that I
often wonder if he'd live five more
years you know even five more years
where would his work have taken him what
direction uh I think about this a lot
when people when people say well what
would Marshall mclan say about this or
if Marshall mcclan was here today what
would he say and even on on my own when
I when I'm you know when I have a topic
I'm I'm thinking about researching or
writing I ask myself you know what would
Marshall say about this and the answer
is we have no way of kn because he only
died at the age he wasn't 70 years old
when he died he could have had a lot
more um time to develop his work uh at
the time of his death he'd already
developed his work a lot further than
what most people know about you know his
whole work with the laws of media with
my
father if he had had another five or 10
years how much further would he develop
that work and what would he say about
today with that in mind you know if he
had lived another decade he would have
actually seen the early internet he died
in
um I think about these things but you
know number 69 uh brings to mind to me
uh project 69 which uh was a grant
awarded by the
naeb the National Association of
educational broadcasters from Washington
DC to Marsha mclen in order to to uh
undergo a study in understanding New
Media um this was in 1958 Marshall
received this uh important Grant
foundational grant for him um the first
major Grant he received with his friend
Ted Carpenter was in the early
1950s um from the Ford foundation and
that started off uh a culture and
communication seminar they undertook
which was an early interdisciplin AR
study of
communication which turned into for for
Marshall and others the birth of media
studies not simply communication studies
the enlarging of this category from
simple communication to Media to all
human Innovation and its
effects um the the second very important
Grant was this Nae Grant which um gave
Marshall the
resources uh to undergo serious study of
Technology and media and the results of
his studies for the next 2 years 58 to
60 um would really underpin and inform
the rest of his his work for the next uh
two decades
almost this is when Marshall came up
with this formulation the medium is the
message among among other things um it's
when when
Marshall uh received this grant which
was for essentially to create
a high school curriculum for
understanding
media um Marshall said about uh doing
that and he delivered it in in What's
called the report on the project in
understanding New Media which he
delivered to the naeb in
1960 um this report didn't really go
anywhere uh within the neb it didn't
become the United States or Canada's
High School curriculum for understanding
media although it would be if it had uh
it kind of fell flat um I think you know
like like a lot of M's work people
didn't know what to do with it right uh
laws of media which may we'll talk about
as well um was an outgrowth of this
whole process and again people didn't
know what to do with in fact nobody
would publish it up until my father
managed to convince somebody in 19888
years after Marshall died but um what
Marshall did was he took this report and
he spent the next four years 1960 to
1964 um revising it chopping it down
taking it apart putting it back together
rewriting and rewriting um basically
condensing it down into poetry and it
was published in 1964 as understanding
media the extensions of
man so this was Marshall taking um and
it's fascinating to look at the report
that he delivered in 1960 uh because
stylistically it's so much different
you would almost think it's completely
different material um but it's not it's
the the book through mcra Hill is
basically um just another version you
know as if you were to make a film from
a book this is making a book from a
report uh in many
senses um and so in making in making a a
popular book from the report uh he did
some interesting
things for one thing there's there's a
narrative structure um at work in in the
book understanding media um it opens up
with you know after 3,000 years of print
dominance essentially um you know it's a
shock to find out that the medium is the
message the book is
essentially um rests on top of the story
of the change between eras from the uh
the alphabet mechanistic era to the
electric era which we
currently uh still riding out I I I feel
like to me I I put it like this you know
if if the alphabet the ultimate
extension of the alphabet was the
technique of fragmentation you know
coming to a peak with the Industrial Age
in the late 19th early 20s Century um
you know perhaps right now we are at a
similar extension of the technique of
electricity with digitization in AI it
feels like a like an apt
comparison um and it would be it would
be interesting to to rewrite this
narrative uh rewrite this book of tools
and information on the top of that
narrative rather than the switch from
mechanistic to electrical but from elect
electrical to digitize to AI which I
think is more of a a transition in out
growth than than a straight up flip OFA
but um you know the one the one
enduring uh interest of Marshall was in
um as he said understanding the
processes uh in which we are
involved he was um this is this was his
preoccupation with with media and
structure and form over content uh
meaning uh which again is an interesting
tension and Paradox because he was an
English teacher and and he was very very
interested in content um he he loved
content you know he loved poetry that
was his his thing poetry and literature
his specialty um media studies was his
was a side hustle that he kind of fell
into and kind of overtook everything
else but his interests uh in both
subjects were the same he was interested
in structure and effect um that was his
interest in poetry and literature which
grew out of his work at Cambridge
University studying under um people like
uh
Lis F Lis and I Richards who founded
practical
criticism um you know mclan work is
essentially uh practical criticism
applied to technology and culture over
simply literature and poetry um so this
was was mclin's enduring interest
structure and effect um effect of
structure and form rather than simply uh
meaning and effective content um you
know that's more toward media literacy
and propaganda uh studies which again
are important but they're um and they're
related obviously but they're separate
categories uh and you know our our
interests tend to be more toward uh
structure and form rather than
content uh which isn't to say again that
content is is meaningless or ineffective
because obviously it is but um you know
the main point of understanding media is
that the the main effects in reshaping
people individually and people
culturally and societally comes less
from the content or uses to which
Technologies are put and more from the
structure of the Technologies itself as
they reshape us and reshape our
environment which then reshape us
again and again so um so that's my my
opening Gambit I
guess
awesome what what a
Gambit for those who are watching
live let's grab some questions use a
live stream mediatic affordance there's
just many places to um jump in where
where would you like to
start well for one thing I want to know
what's happening with the the the
pyramid triangle set up behind you
there good question I use a lot of
tetrahedra to symbolize Bucky Fuller
synergetics and the different first
principle the different starting point
in synergetics as opposed to kind of the
water we swim in today is rather than
starting with a three-dimensional XYZ
Cube starting with a tetrahedron four
events the minimum enclosed system kind
of comes up again in active inference
with the fourfold particular partition
and so it just reminds me that space is
not necessarily cubic and that even
our space and time
projection is heavily in feedback with
the angles that we see so I look forward
I see 0° angle and I can imagine space
is cubic but then I can look back and
see that it doesn't have to be that way
okay can you can you back up a second
and talk a little bit more about active
inference in the fourfold what now yes
so to the fourfold of active inference
um one of the key developments of active
inference though it's in the tradition
of cybernetics and ecological psychology
is heavily rest ing upon um a particular
partition and so it's a little bit of a
pun because it's that specific
particular way to partition Agents from
the environment and then also what it
individuates is called the particle and
so the first cleaving is the environment
from the agent so the external States
from the particle and then the particle
itself there's a
three-fold which is the income sensory
information the internal cognitive
States and then the outgoing action
dependencies and so the incoming sensory
States and outgoing action states that
defines like the blanket or the
interface so the particle sometimes is
described as the interface plus the
internals or to zoom in on the blanket
or the interface there's the
incoming aspect of the interface the
sense and then there's the out goinging
dependencies on the blanket which is the
action and then everything that happens
behind the back black box that's the
cognitive internal
States okay that's interesting it's um
it's not unrelated to um something I've
been working on for for quite a while
which is uh a mclan model of
communication or of media um which does
not exist really when you look when you
look up models of
communication um mclan isn't in the
conversation
uh which is interesting and I I felt
that was a a significant Gap um and
that's that's led me to I've been toying
with this for a year or so anyway you
know um but against for example the
Shannon Weaver model of communication
where you have you know the source and
then the message to be shipped somewhere
and then received um the mclan model
uh is a bit deeper than that you know
Marshall says that um Shannon Weaver is
a model of Transportation you know
moving information from one place to
another um and his is a model of
transformation or what happens along the
way and at the end you know how we are
changed again effect right so how you
know I stare I've got it over there on a
board and I look at this Weaver model
and think how to
include uh
mclin's ideas Notions about technology
and its effects into a model uh a trans
what does a transformation model look
like graphically and it's it's some it's
a little bit related to what you were
talking about with particular
partition
um but uh the main the main area of
focus is is on the
senses so um the impact of of
information or data or stimulus
stimuli um on our senses because uh the
way you hear people talk about it it's
as if the these senses are are static
things and they're not uh or they're
passive things and they're not um the
you know the data the information is is
color is received uh but the way it's
received is has everything to do with
the nature of the senses receiving it
and uh the senses don't simply it's not
like a straw right that you suck liquid
through um because uh you know it's it's
very much transformed and we are
transformed reciprocally right there's
there's a reciprocal thing that happens
um the other thing uh which needs to be
taken into account is that when we talk
about the senses when we think about the
senses um we need to think about them
individually but we also need to think
about them
collectively because our our senses our
bodily senses our interior
senses um they all exist in a balance in
a ratio among themselves you know we
speak of the
sensorium as one thing and that again is
not a static thing it's a dynamic thing
uh to change to affect one sense is to
affect all the
senses uh by either numbing them or
activating and when you alter a sense um
you alter all the other senses because
you alter the relationship among them if
you if you go if you well if you even
close your
eyes uh you know when you're trying to
hear something uh really closely you
close your eyes and kind of Point your
ear toward it right cuz you want to cut
off the visual faculty which is
dominating things and you want to focus
all your energy toward that sense um
when people go blind uh they almost
universally talk about how their other
senses perk up um that's because your
senses react and they pick up the slack
and they change you uh fundamentally you
know mechanically as to who you are but
also um how you identify you know how
you see yourselves how others see you
right for example if I were a blind
person your background there would have
no significance for me uh or for you
right like you would probably be sitting
in front of blank walls maybe white
maybe not who knows who cares right they
have zero meaning uh but that little
assembly behind you is a reflection and
and a impact act F and necessary
reflection of your identity um you know
I went through a house fire when I was a
teenager uh and it's an awful thing but
every just to bit everything I own
burned up in it including all my
clothing and you don't realize how much
of our identity especially as a kid is
wrapped up in your
wardrobe right I had to go out shopping
I went to the local Walmart and bought a
couple outfits of things and I'm wearing
it and I don't feel like me I'm somebody
else
you know little changes like this um
have have big effects on an individual
level right so when you mess with your
senses when you rearrange their balance
you change who you are individually you
put those individuals together and you
have a society a culture you know um it
change it changes in your senses affect
you individually and affect you
culturally this is uh very much the
underpinning of of mcluen work where
where where the medium is the message is
because it's not the content that messes
with your senses the content is the
delivery mechanism paradoxically for the
changes introduced by the medium you
know and it's in this sense that the
content is irrelevant you know it it
doesn't really matter so much if we're
talking about this or if we're talking
about beehives or tetrahedrons or
whatever else you know uh the content is
just what's keeping us occupied while
these forces are in action and shaping
us so uh you know as it says in
understanding media I love how Marshall
um paraphrases so many different people
in that book but TS Elliott he
paraphrased when he said that content is
the juicy piece of meat used by the
burglar to distract the Watchdog of the
mind and that's what he's talking about
you know the content is what Keeps Us
busy and uh unaware while this
rearrangement is happening quite between
beneath our notice you know uh as he
said also everybody experiences far more
than they
understand
amazing I'll make a few points and then
ask some questions from live chat
so sense also has a broad scope in
active inference because sense is just
used to cover all inbound dependencies
so that could include sensories uh
sensus changing within a lifetime
differential
accessibility um or just different ways
of modeling inputs of system so sense is
super broad on the incoming sens making
side action is all outgoing
dependencies all the kinds of behaviors
that emit from a system so that's why
the theory of the interface and
conditioning on the interface and the
boundary or the blanket that that's such
a key move that allows the conditioning
upon particularity um and then also like
given that kind of multimodal Sense
Technology objects come in
bundles um the smell and the mass and
the look and the sound they do all
co-occur in the product and in the
material reality of media and then even
if that weren't the case like somehow
bizarrely attention would still have its
own d IC so so much of the brunt of the
receipt of information um rather than
falling into this payload content
deliverable packet envelope like it's
kind of this naive like well the meaning
is right there on the pages right there
in the book and then it's like being
like well yes once you've zeroed out the
fact that it's a letter you can abstract
the information and talk about it maybe
in a more General um or or
dematerialized or however it's um seen
but but the Primacy which is so um
glaring is our sensory perception and
active perception with the icate the
blind spot the low resolution Vision in
the periphery these features that belyy
the generative nature of our experience
period and we know that there's
frequencies that we don't pick up like
radio and then radio appears and all
sudden that changes our sensory
environment so this is a um very
[Music]
fun exercise to see how many of these
concordances which were observed um and
intuited and worked
after in the mclan tradition how many of
these because they're grounded in like
qualitative Prima fascia aspects of
experience yeah their applicability is
like higher than a computer science
paper from 1975 which isn't to say that
it wasn't super informative for moving
the field forward to 1976 but then like
the shelf life dropped and the older
things that took longer in terms of the
change to understand they start to like
punch way above their weight and also
it's cool to connect all the dots in
conversation yeah I mean um a large part
of the reason why U Marshall mclan work
remains vital and important in our time
is because um he examines media as a
category and talks about media in
general and not
simply different media in particular you
know if all his work was just studying
television then you know obviously it
wouldn't have much to say about today
um but this book understanding media for
example is uh if you look at it it's two
parts part one is seven chapters and
part two is 26 chapters coming again to
new numbers in numerology and not
accidental um you know Marshall favored
the
trivan but uh we have what classical
education was modeled on the Seven
Liberal
Arts so that's the Trivium of writing uh
sorry of grammar dialectic and rhetoric
and it's the quadrivium of astronomy
math music and arith uh I always forget
one of them anyway uh I consider I think
about part one of understanding media as
mcl's Seven Liberal Arts uh Seven
Liberal Arts of media because what it is
is it is each of those chapters is a
different perspective a different way of
looking at any techn technology any
human Innovation not just Communications
media but if you look at at part two the
chapters go from speech to clothing to
housing to cars to television it's human
Innovation it's not just
communication it's technology it's
anything that we do to increase uh you
know the abilities we're born with
essentially and that's what Marshall is
studying so each of those first seven
chapters and you'll get a lot from the
book if you look at it this way each of
those chapters is one perspective or
method or way of looking at Technologies
part two is taking these seven
principles from part one and applying
them on particular Technologies and
putting that in action that's why this
book is so great and it's perennial and
ever green because it's it's a guide
book uh not simply situated in uh you
know technology up to 196 4 but useful
today it's wild that you know I've read
the book several times I've LED two
groups of students through it from cover
to cover word by word in a process
that's 36 2 or three hour
classes and every
time I lead people through that book
it's as if the book was written today to
talk about what's happening today
because it was
that's
wild awesome and aside plot is Bucky
Fuller and Marshall knowing each other
and Bucky saying that he was 50 years on
time and what was 50 years ago from now
all these very fun yeah topics I'm gonna
ask some questions in the live chat and
we'll just continue to see where it goes
okay sure upcycle Club wrs so cool I
have a question for Andrew can you share
any interesting anecdotes or stories
about your grandfather and his work that
may not be widely
known
um uh I mean like what in you have to be
a little more specific that's uh okay
well we'll get a followup um from cycle
club next question the intuitive artist
writes how is context contextuality
recontextualization understood within
the
model
um yeah so that's a great
question context
contextuality um you
know It's Tricky talking about media and
looking at uh mclan in
media um you know it's a very good
question to ask well what does he mean
by Media or what is a
medium um as It's tricky because uh you
know like a lot of human uh a lot of
English the English language and other
languages um a single word can have
several meanings right uh the word
medium is no different because medium
can be can be used to talk about an
instrument uh like a a specific medium
like the pen or it can be used as a
right it can be used as a word to talk
about uh like a growing medium a culture
an
environment um and it's interesting to
me that uh understanding media comes
keep in mind again that understanding
media is published in
1964 but the source material was written
1958 to 1960 and Rewritten and Rewritten
and Rewritten until it was published in
64 but um as that that art comes along
uh one of one of the very very important
pieces in the cluing Canon is a work
published in the at the end of 1965 or
written uh it's dated November 1965
called the relation of environment to
anti-environment this is a very very
important
piece um and a lot of it has to do with
the senses he says um we have we have no
reason to be grateful to those who
juggled this uh sensory thresholds in
the name of halfhazard information I
love this line this one of my favorite
lines we have no reason to be grateful
to those who juggle the sensory ratios
in the name of halfhazard
innovation he's talking about inventors
and technology companies uh people who
create these new tools um who
essentially are creating devices which
juggle our sensory thresholds um you
know the the tolerances of our senses
you know the individual quality of each
sense um where where they Peak uh how
much they're used the ratio among them
that every new technology when it when
it you know is used essentially um
affects those senses re Jiggles rewires
remodels them affects them individually
and collect collectively and creates at
the at the end you know a particular
balance of the
senses um the new technologies that come
along uh juggle these sensory thresholds
in the name of haaz Innovation so like
we design a
technology to be able to make phone
calls as we're out and about or listen
to music on the go or whatever whatever
other objective or aim we have but the
the effect is always uh much different
than the objective right um the side
effects always end up adding up to more
than the main effects or the intended
effects the intended effects are one
thing the actual effects are another and
so it's he calls it halfhazard
Innovation because we don't actually
plan for most of what the effects are um
however I think uh you know I'm I'm
drifting a little bit away from from the
context question but not really
um Marshall's object um sometimes
expressed in this term media ecology was
to take more control over these effects
because um he said you know there's
absolutely no inevitability as long as
there's a willingness to uh comprehend
the situation to pay attention the thing
is uh you know the environments any
environment is a very Dynamic active
large complicated place um and as I said
before everybody experiences so much
more than they understand there's so
much I mean in your own body there's so
much happening right now that's quite
beneath your level of awareness you're
breathing the blood flowing through your
body
oxygenized or you know growing sharper
all these things are happening um quite
underneath your notice um if you think
about your body as an environment but
think about a larger environment which
only only gets uh more complex you know
um but we don't we don't generally think
about the larger environment or
ecosystem when we uh design things we
tend to have a very very narrow Focus um
although it was Marshall's contention
that we didn't need to be you know there
there doesn't need to be any ignorance
in these matters once we understand that
there's anything that we're not paying
attention to right um so his idea of
taking control of Technology um had a
lot to do with a kind of
environmentalism an environmental
activism more than you know the silly
stuff that happens in Congress and and
whatever else where they argue about
censorship and people's rights and all
this stuff which uh well anyway that's
another another subject isn't it well
just one short comment on that and then
I'll ask a question from the live chat
media if we say something like
mainstream media it's kind of like oh
yeah it's a newspaper or it's the
internet or the TV but it's this kind of
whatever it is whereas in the art World
Media or in the scientific laboratory
culture media is the growth medium and
so it's the medium of creation and that
allies it essentially only entirely with
ecological psychology and it's more of a
um
secondary connection
or a secondary use that it's applied to
what we call the media in terms of
communications apparatuses by multiple
names yeah um you know I mentioned uh
anti-environment and that's it's not a
term that you hear uh you can Marshall
MCL was essentially as he defined it an
anti-environmentalist although I never
heard him use it quite that way um an
anti-environment is essentially
any device or situation that helps you
apprehend an
environment okay so it's like putting
dye in in the water in order to to
follow the flow of of a stream or
underground current right that's an
anti-environment um Marshall categorized
artists as anti-
environments um because they're people
or you know the Court Jester who's there
to point out things that people are
missing as uncomfortable as they might
be um and it's generally
uncomfortable this is actually you know
people don't don't generally think about
it this way but um Marshall
MCL uh had an object you know he he had
uh an intent a mission that he was
undertaking and that that intention was
um to wake people up to the things
happening around them in the name of
halfhazard
innovation to understand
that um you
know technology the content level the
understanding the meaning level is just
the very very tip of the iceberg in
terms of what we do um when we
mediate yes yet another sense of media
to mediate intermediate all right I'll
read a comment and then a question from
the chat
so Dean writes sensory attenuation
so the suppressing of attention would
seem to play an important role in an
effects based approach to understanding
media and here's a question from Chris
Bennett who wrote how does the move to
AR VR compared to the move from printed
media to
radio
um that's a good
question uh you know this term AR
augmented reality uh makes me laugh a
little bit because um any technology
augments reality you know Alters to
alter our perception is to alter our
reality um you know for all intents and
purposes um but the move move to say it
again the move from from print to radio
and the
move the current move implied from a to
AR VR big if okay compar to the move
from printed media to
radio yeah well you know it's
interesting
um another another one of the tools from
understanding media the second chapter
um which confuses a lot of people is uh
media hot and
cool hot and cool media and these are
relative terms um you know I think about
the temperature of the water is it hot
is it cold they're relative terms right
compared to one another um what's what's
hot compared to one thing might be cold
compared to another thing right very
relative terms but um Marshall the way
Marshall used them for for
examining if not understanding Media or
technology is uh again it comes down to
sense the
senses and um it's it's a bit of another
equation which which runs a little bit
like this um
that the the more information the the
quality of the information that is how
rich it is in intensity uh coming at you
or complete or incomplete um has a
proportionate response from you so um if
you're if you're given a lot of
information like in a photograph for
example a photograph is very rich
visually very full of information
um a high
definition um it doesn't require a lot
from you to um to make sense so to speak
right to get something from
it uh a cartoon in contrast is very low
in definition very low in information
compared to a photograph for example in
a cartoon you have uh you know you
usually a very simple representation of
something and a narrative sequence that
there's a lot happening between frames
you know that you kind of fill in it
requires a lot from you in order to make
something of it to complete this is what
Marshall is talking about when he talks
about
participation um often times it's not so
much active participation but sensory
participation like uh in film right in
in film traditional film that is what
you have actually is a is a sequence of
still images that speed up enough in
order to trick the eye into seeing
movement um in in sequential movement uh
in natural flowing movement which
actually isn't isn't there it's it's a
rapid sequence of of still images um
you're involved to a very deep extent in
keeping up this illusion and making
sense of the thing making it work versus
video which is has a completely
different character um so one way to to
look at the nature of Any Given
technology is to analyze it in terms of
its definition and the image or
information proferred um to know what
kind of effect it has in return and uh
it's the demand that it makes
um and what that you know means in
return so uh from print to
radio well you're dealing with very
different sensory spaces for one thing
um you know the print print which uh
involves the eye and occupies the eye um
and radio which involves uh is very much
lower uh in information obviously lower
in visual
information uh you it keeps your mind
busy making pictures and stuff um in a
different way than the than the visual
does uh AR and
VR are very very rich uh you know if hot
is high definition these are very very
hot things um they don't leave much for
for you to do but sit sit and stare
right
it's interesting the reactions people
are having to Apple Vision
Pro um it's almost a religious
experience it's so
rich uh it's interesting to me
that the way that screens operate you
know with the light coming
through one of our our first
Technologies using the light through
principle were stained glass
windows as as if we we almost
intuitively
understood How Deeply religious an
effect an experience it
has yes well the Curiosity what's on the
other side of the blanket what's on the
other side of the veil what's on the
other side of the interface like it's
kind of the unknowable but that's where
the Mind imagines and then to return to
your earlier point about like the impact
of information so there's the syntax of
data just in a digital setting it's like
is it a 1080p video is it 4K is it 8K is
it 360 video so all these kind of
brandings and resolution differences
that's definitely part of the um
experience and then there's the
semantics and there might be a super
high resolution photo with one object
there might be a low resolution photo of
many objects and then it comes up
through the recipient dependent
unpacking all the way on through like
narrative consequences so there could be
a high resolution photo and someone
could flip through vacation photos very
rapidly and take in a gigabyte of data
and then some pixels of a stick figure
could be very shocking for them and have
this total influence and so that's part
of the multifaceted challenge of talking
about like information and communication
and
media understanding that it is kind of
all last mile
and
yet the challenge and the task is to
make those kinds of Timeless artifacts
that are of pragmatic and epistemic
value in future
moments yeah you know it's it's really
interesting to me that
um generative AI is typically used to
make uh quote unquote photo realistic
images uh experiences because not just
still images but now video and stuff as
well um whereas there's there seems to
be a
parallel um this 8bit
16bit uh you know GIF Crypt Punk crypto
stuff uh is at the complete opposite end
of that that spectrum because that's
very very very low definition I've yet
to see anybody using mid Journey or
whatever else to to produce low
definition
experiences um they seem to be geared
toward very very high definition
experiences which uh I don't know what
it means it's just an interesting
observation to me yeah one interesting
part with the writing and with the
images is partially through training and
so on on people's approval it generates
hyper Salient or hyper normative types
of content relative to what it's trained
upon of course this the topic we can go
into but it just always so overblown and
intense like a movie poster and just but
always taken to like the nth
degree rather than the kind of looking
like it's from the 1990s like very
normal photo realism that has still more
of a real flavor than the
hypernormal and all of these kinds of
things okay up psycho Club is back with
a specification okay I will try to make
my question more explicit smiley face
do you have a story to share about your
grandfather's interest in the Fisher
spasy chess match and how he related it
to his media
theory if you could summarize that if
you know about it that would be fun
um I don't
uh you know I I have very
few um first person anecdotes to share
about Marshall uh
because um I was a baby when he died uh
I was you know 2 years old I was born in
the summer of 78 and he died in the
winter of 80 so um you know I was not
quite two years old but uh oh sorry I
was two and a half years old
um the interesting thing to me
is it's really wild to see pictures of
of him holding me as a as a kid um I was
just starting to talk you know I was
making noises and he had had a a major
stroke um the previous year the fall of
1979 and he couldn't
talk uh he could only just kind of
Babble and make
noises and I was I've been told that um
we had great conversations with each
other that nobody outside of us could
understand whether we understood each
other or simply enjoyed each other I
don't know know um I I wish I could
remember maybe there's some kind of
regressive hypnotherapy that could
surface some things I don't know um I
don't think I need to go there I think I
can enjoy the knowledge that it happened
and you know that we were able
to enjoy each other's presence like that
um you
know when people know about that time of
his life that he lived the last last 18
or so months of his life um unable to
communicate uh in the manner in which he
was accustomed and listen the manner to
which he was accustomed was he had such
an active mind um and his he worked it
out in dialogue uh mostly orally you
know speaking to himself to others to
whoever happened to be around whether
they wanted to hear it or not um
to have that suddenly cut off a lot of
people um talk about the irony you know
or the
tragedy that um this guy could no longer
do
that and I think um certainly at first
uh it would have been a shock and and
horrible um you know to only be able to
make yourself understood through
gestures and you know very basic things
like that uh to not be able to express
the thoughts that you're having maybe
not to be able to have the thoughts that
you're used to having um much less write
them down or speak them uh certainly a
kind of torture at
times however
um I think there's a lot of relief in
there
too that not being able to provide that
function not being able to to do that
um frees you from having to do
it um I see pictures from that time uh a
visit that he made to Ted Carpenter on
Long Island uh playing around in in the
ocean with Ted Carpenter and the biggest
smile on his face the biggest Smiles
you've never seen somebody so
happy
uh there's a freedom there a great
freedom and
when robbed or relieved depending on how
you want to look at it of the ability
and the necessity to communicate
deeply if you want to get any enjoyment
out of
life uh you have to find it where you
can and uh I like to think that myself
my
sisters uh I didn't oh yeah there was a
cousin or two around at that point um I
know where I find my Pleasures you know
I have two young
kids uh and a wife and our relationship
just being with each other is so
fulfilling and uh I think for the first
time maybe in his life certainly in you
know a long time he was he was able to
enjoy the simpler things communing with
his
family communing with his God you know I
would imagine a lot of prayer
uh and and that kind of experience would
happen in those
circumstances um you know sometimes our
biggest challenges are our biggest
opportunities well thank you for sharing
that that was very special
and you said he was robbed or
relieved essentially at this partial
removal from the oral discourse
community of which he wrote and spoke so
much
about and to have the crossover
point on the the Rising Sun and the
Setting Sun of
language and uh that that uh and then
even how
much do those special events need to be
dissected or what does dissection
do when the
media ecosystem rolls forward and
doesn't dissect the fermentation of the
past but thank you and upcycle Club says
thank you as
well you're welcome upcycle
Club where would you like to take it or
what's a a question or a thought or I
can read something else from the live
chat yeah go ahead what's the the live
chat guy okay okay Richard writes
mcluhan called the age of movable type
is fragmented and the electronic age is
global but it seems the situation is the
opposite a small number of books were
common to all literates but Electronic
media is targeted to each consumer
differently Mojo writes good to view
them in the light of Markov blankets and
how they maintain themselves through
perturbations and social movements and
this is something that like we've
explored a lot in active inference and
the social sciences is well what does a
formalism do for the Social and how do
we approach and tackle and address the
social in all of its complexities and
what does going into that forest with
this formalism toolkit do is the
formalism or the toolkit in account oh
yeah the social group no worries just
generative model
and then what dust it off and walk away
so how do we see the formalism as the
beginning of an investigation and
inquiry rather than how it's sometimes
positioned in like a disciplinary or
learning environment that the framework
of the abstraction is the Terminus of
the inquiry and bend the attention back
to addressing specific
systems
H I've never I I'm not familiar with was
marov
Blanket yes it's a topic in active it's
on a base graph when there's some
variables that insulate other variables
so like earlier talking about the sense
as the incoming dependencies and the
action as the outgoing
dependencies another exactly equivalent
way to say that is the external states
only influence the internal States
through sense and the internal states
only influence the external States
through action and another way to say
that is no telepathy no
telekinesis just at a first pass but
there's an interface that is
insulating the cognitive
States and the affective and the
bodily is insulated off from just
coarsely let's just say the video studio
and what they're broadcasting it's
moving through a medium mhm and then
there's the semantic unpacking and if
something was shown but you weren't
paying attention to it then it was as
good as not there versus if something
was seen that that wasn't there in the
mind of the broadcaster that's kind of a
nonse because that's what is happening
yeah interesting
[Music]
um of
course again there's that quote that U
you know we experience far much more
than we understand you know you don't
you don't have to understand anything
about effects to register and be
affected by things you know um oh
there's I wondered when bar would show
up this cat honestly I was giving a
guest lecture last night for NYU class
and this cat is literally sitting back
here going meow meow meow meow the whole
time I'm like trying to gather my
thoughts and this cat is like heckling
me uh well played Barry damn
um yeah again you know environments and
and anti- environments but uh there's
this uh funny exchange it's it's on the
internet of course on YouTube um
Buckminster Fuller Marshall mclen and wh
aen on a panel together uh debating
television discussing debating
television and uh one of my favorite
lines from that is you know a in is you
know a playwright guy he's very anti-
television and he like know television I
wouldn't I wouldn't dream of of having
television and and Marshall says well
you merely suffer the consequences
without enjoying any of the
benefits and the point there is that you
don't need to have a
television you don't need to watch
television to be affected by the
television as a medium as you know
something which is running our society
same with
smartphones you might not have a
smartphone but you live in a society
that runs on the
smartphone so
um it's interesting What marshall is
saying here CU he's almost saying well
you know you might as well have it and
get some benefit some use some enjoy out
of the thing if you're going to be
affected by it anyway right but he's
he's being kind of tongue and cheek
about
that uh but still the point the point
remains and you know it's the nature of
of an environment is that um there's uh
there's little Escape we we have only
the
crudest uh ways of maintaining an
environment a technological environment
um one way is uh to do what some Amish
or hutterite uh communities do which is
they impose techn hard technological
limits you know it's like they basically
freeze technology at the uh level to
which because it's interesting they they
understand um even if it's
unconsciously that to introduce these
different Technologies would destroy
their culture they're not wrong they're
they're quite right about
it um and the only the only thing we can
do at this point is to uh protect our
environment from it right Walling off a
community it's you know the crudest it's
crude but effective you know a much more
sophisticated way to do it would be well
what is it about this
technology that would interrupt what we
value from our community and then to
design the technology accordingly like
but that requires a really really deep
understanding
of uh the instrument and and again it
really comes down to sensory things
because you know
generally cultures protectionist
cultures like this are trying to protect
um specific parts of their
culture
and uh that's a very very difficult um
things to do in the face of change isn't
it bar
yeah um but it is you know it may be it
may be crude but
effective
um it's one thing you know I live I've
got two kids as I mentioned
uh they're six and 8 years old and uh
well they're just about to turn sorry
eight and 10 years
old which is crazy but
um uh or Sorry Seven and N how old are
my kids again gez time what is time but
uh it's it's very it's very difficult to
be a parent uh
today especially when you understand as
I do how
important technology
is in shaping who your kids are becoming
as
people uh it's wild I see and again
parenting I think is the toughest gig do
you have any kids Daniel not yet okay
parenting is a toughest gig and I have
so much respect from other parents
because
it's difficult um and you know I don't
want to judge anybody and tell people
that they're doing it right or wrong
it's context situations are different
but you know I
see uh I also know too much you know I
understand uh what happens cognitively
and sensorily when you're exposed to
different Technologies I know that um
the society the person brought up uh
around lit literature in the environment
of literature versus the person brought
up in an environment absence of
literature and rich in technology like
screens televisions smartphones
Etc um are tend to produce very
different
results uh your brain your senses are
wired in particular Pathways um that set
you up for
life um which isn't to say they don't
change cuz they do
um you know our senses our brains these
things are plastic they're elastic to a
certain extent but they're set up in in
the first couple of years of life so uh
you know Marshall at one point is in an
understanding media wonders out loud
about uh people developing the habits of
literacy after being raised on
television and wondering if this isn't
uh not a great way to go around it if
the process should be perhaps reversed
um the difficulty is the barrier to
entry you know so I see I see a kid in a
baby carriage right is isn't old enough
to walk on their own without falling
over and the parent hands them a
smartphone or an i a tablet right an
iPad whatever and the kid pokes at it
and is Off to the Races can do a lot of
things
versus drop drop this into a kids slap
right in the baby carriage and what's it
going to do it's going to eat it that's
about all it can do is chew on it it
takes it takes years and years and years
in order to open this and to to make
this these Pages these letters whatever
do anything for you you know not even
any any pictures unless the kids a fan
of you know concrete poetry or something
at the age of one or two it's not going
to get very far
it's um so you know these things versus
each other it's obvious which one is
going to win right this is um and this
sets up the kid uh in a certain way
versus versus this um but I get it
parenting is a tough gig and uh God I
just want some peace and quiet sometimes
myself you know and it's easy to give a
kid a device and they keep themselves
happy for hours and hours and hours in
fact um the average American citizen
between the ages of8 and 18 now consumes
eight and a half hours of non of screen
time every day for non-educational
purposes is the statistic so this
doesn't count um the screen time for
school or for educational
purposes and that right there tells you
so much about the lack of understanding
on the part of government agencies
because they make a distinction between
educational and
non-educational as if it's a distinction
that makes a difference when it comes
down to the sensory neurological
psychological sensory cultural identity
effects of Technologies these things do
not occur on the level of opinions
Concepts or
content at
all uh and every time we get a new
statistic that says something like that
it shows how little our understanding
has come and how far we have to go if
we're ever going to make any Headway and
take any control over our technological
lives and the direction of
culture which is an easy thing to say
from this side of the
screen thank you that's very powerful
and it just makes me think about how the
the payload
content the meaning is inside of the
envelope perspective leads to these
ideological distinctions and lines and
shifting in the sand and all this but
that's kind of like an adult literary
discussion like well here's a quote word
this word was used this way but while
that debate was happening or discussion
or whatever um the the baseball diamond
and the sports field have been
transformed with screens such that
basically no matter where in a downtown
area or like even in restaurants or on a
train even things that when I was
younger were not
seen so where's the discussion around
that and part of it is hindered by just
like you describe like that kind of um
affordance at hand and the kind of low
activation energy um so the concept that
it's a personal choice however
everything can kind of be understood in
terms of personal choice and constraint
too um and just how that whole semantics
discussion
like is on a
separate concept of
media than what is happening moment to
moment for like 8.5 or
18.5 hours per day with complete
permanent consequences on
everything yeah it's wild um you know
I understanding as I do these
things um I try to spend as little time
on the screen as I can uh but it's still
a lot of time um whenever I I'm able to
uh I read something off off the page
rather than the screen I've got you know
6,000 books here for example
um and my ideal is to try and balance
right like spend as much time reading uh
as I do on screens and it's impossible
it's a daily battle that I'm losing big
time you know emails and correspondences
and things like this and um you know I'd
much rather have this conversation in
person uh but this
is the reality of things and you know
what this this reality of things also
means I can do a lot that I wouldn't
other other be able to do cuz I'm
talking to you here from a 19th Century
Barn in rural Southern
Ontario um from here because of my
internet access I'm able to lead courses
on understanding media that have 20 30
students from around the world joining
me for a couple hours a week for 36
weeks um simply because of of the fact
this circumstance this medium this
environment of services and disservices
and for all the disservices it it makes
things possible that would otherwise not
be because if I were to hold this class
here I don't think I'd get a
student you know I don't think I'd get a
a single person come uh certainly not
enough to make it make sense and this is
why I think about it um I think about it
like like New York City New York City is
my ideal cuz you know uh anything
anything is possible there with 8
million
people uh at your doorstep
essentially you can open up uh a small
shop that you know caters to Buckminster
Fuller Dome building kits or something
and probably make a living you know out
of 8 million people your community
a community can coales can assemble can
find each other can exist and support uh
the internet brings 8 billion people
potentially to my barn you know it means
I can connect um in the same way that
that New York City can and you know try
to make a modest living out of what I do
so as much as uh you know obviously
that's
that's the thing that make Tech makes
technology work um is the affordance is
the things that makes possible and we
just have to deal with the Fallout and
with the things that it makes
impossible uh the things that it you
know one environment sustains certain
things and and not others um I talk we
talk a big game about the senses and
media ecology and being more intentional
about design but it is essentially
theoretical um because I'm not building
Hardware or software or anything else
although I am talking to people who
are um and that's why I'm trying to
reach people who are designing the
technologies that are going to be
creating the environments of tomorrow um
this is I think our greatest area of
opportunity um and it's actually why I
remain very hopeful you know because
uh
again mixed blessings but it's never
been
easier uh the barriers keep dropping
away you know the technological change
happens so quickly now because such
powerful tools are at our fingertips our
literal
fingertips um you know even 30 years ago
you didn't have the access to
supercomputers uh shared time and stuff
um relatively affordable things access
to information computing power building
things uh now is easier for younger
people to do this is where I think
there's hope
because um it's easier for younger
people to follow their dreams and their
ideals younger
people uh want to do
you know I think everybody a lot of
people want to do the right thing but
it's easier for younger people to
actually do the right thing because they
have left to Lo less to lose you know
here I am approaching middle age or
whatever I have kids I've got a mortgage
you know bills to pay uh I got to do
what I got to do um but you know a
teenager people in their young 20s and
startups developing Technologies they
don't have a house they don't have kids
they have fewer responsibilities fewer
fears they can follow those their hearts
and their dreams and now with the access
to tools and services and computing
power and things um and financing
particularly they don't have to take
they don't have to make hard decisions
that other people used to have to do you
know um they don't have to take money
from one place uh there's another place
to take money from funding you know and
this gives me hope um because as I said
I think they're more more likely because
they're in a better position maybe to do
uh to
make harder choices that are maybe
easier for them sorry that's a very
fuzzy and convoluted way of trying to
express what I'm trying to express but I
hope it comes
through thank you well as we sort of
land the plane
exp where and how are you going to
continue your work and also I would love
to hear a little bit about the
consequences or implications for
education and for online for example
technical online education and all these
different things like
that sure yeah um I
mean I'm I'm going to keep on keeping on
pretty much uh I've got you know what
I'm trying to do here is preserve the
work and the way of work that my
grandfather started back in the 40s and
50s that my my father jumped in and kept
going uh from the 60s through the 80s
and 90s and early
thousands um and I've been left with a
lot of
stuff uh in physical form and a lot of
begun projects and half finish things um
and my role which I take on with
absolute Delight is to preserve that and
make it
available uh for today and
tomorrow um how I do that I'm still
figuring
out uh you know I'm independent you know
the mclan Institute is essentially me
it's not uh it's not a registered
business or anything else I'm not
affiliated with any business or other
institution I don't get any government
or private funding really um I've got a
patreon page go ahead and join that if
you want I've got a substack which you
can subscribe to the mclan
newsletter um I sell stuff through my
Bookshop and whatnot uh and basically
the money that I make teaching giving
speeches
Consulting uh you know I pour back into
uh
here
um ideally um you know I would spend
less time doing the exterior stuff and
more time in here doing the work that I
think is more valuable and important but
um you know means to an end and it is
what it is right
now um the
future uh you know I don't think people
for a long time I don't think people
have gone to school to really get an
education uh to learn important
things um going to school has more been
about you know because that's why
universities were begun is centralized
knowledge to make it available for
people but um as many people have
pointed out there's more information
available outside the university than in
it at this point and that's been true
for a century or
more um so going to school is more about
socialization networking status
credentials that kind of thing um when
people want to learn things uh that
they're passionate about they they go in
generally I'm speaking very broadly um
they have many other different ways to
do it I've been very fortunate to be
able to offer classes and courses and
stuff for like I said people from around
the world students to retired professors
to professionals across Industries and I
think that is uh increasingly the future
is this uh self-directed
learning um it's interesting that uh
it's happening uh facilitated more and
more from businesses you know people are
encouraged to continue learning to build
their skill set to follow their
interests to develop and grow uh because
change happens so fast um you want
people that are growing not uh
Specialists and kind of dead people
right we all need to keep uh growing and
expanding because this environment and
the things within it keep growing and
expanding uh to stand still is to you
know to die
essentially so um I'm going to I'm going
to keep on doing that uh following my
own nose and interests you know uh doing
my best to translate and interpret and
make available bridging
Generations uh as I can and I'm really
glad to have uh all you along with me
and together for this
ride
amazing I resonate with a lot of that so
thank you for the work and to our
colleague who introduced us and to the
live live chat for many
great topics and questions and let's
stay in touch and maybe 69.2 and then
you know dare I say 69.3 when the time
is
right awesome hey good to talk to you
take care everybody thank you Andrew
peace